I'm delighted to see you again.
다시 만나서 반가워요
As we get started with day three of week three of our adventure and the, uh, things are going to get
모험 3주 차 3일째가 시작됐는데요 이번엔 상황이 더 심화될 거예요
get deeper this time.
get it
We're going to roll our sleeves up as we get into the lower level APIs of hugging Face Transformers
페이스 트랜스포머 포옹 라이브러리 하위 레벨 API를 살펴보면서 팔을 걷어붙일게요. Get
library.
it.
And as always, just a quick reminder you can code against frontier models, you can build AI assistants,
다시 한번 말씀드리지만 프론티어 모델에 대한 코드도 만들 수 있고 인공지능 비서를 만들 수도 있고 파이프라인을
and you can use pipelines.
사용할 수도 있어요
Pipelines.
파이프라인요
What we did last time, such an easy way to use the wide variety of open source inference tasks available
지난번에 했던 건 정말 쉬운 방법이었죠 얼굴을 안는 것으로부터 가능한 다양한 오픈 소스 추론 작업을 사용하는
from Hugging Face.
거요
Today, though, we get lower level.
오늘은 낮은 레벨로 가죠 Get it
As I mentioned, there are these these these two things, tokenizers and models that are part of the
앞서 언급했듯이 토큰라이저와 모델은 파이프라인보다 낮은 수준에서
way we interact with transformers at a lower level than pipelines.
트랜스포머와 상호 작용하는 방법의 일부죠
And that's what we're going to be doing today.
오늘 그걸 할 거예요
We're going to be starting with Tokenizers.
토큰라이저부터 시작할 거예요
We're going to be learning how to translate between text and tokens for different models, and we're
텍스트와 토큰을 다른 모델로 변환하는 법을 배울 거예요 채팅 템플릿이라는
going to be understanding something called chat templates, which I'm hoping is going to make a few
것도 이해할 거고요 이로써 몇 가지 다른 것들이 하나로 합쳐지면
different things come together.
좋겠네요
It's quite an important moment.
중요한 순간이에요
Um, so first, to introduce this type of object called a tokenizer in hugging face, it is an object
먼저, 토큰마이저라는 유형의 객체를 소개할게요 얼굴을 안는 거예요
which translates as you can imagine between text, a string and tokens, a list of numbers.
이 객체는 문자열과 토큰, 숫자 목록을 번역하는 거예요
Um, and there are very simply two functions.
기능은 두 가지로 아주 간단해요
Two things you need to know about encoding and decoding.
암호화와 해독에 관해 알아야 할 게 두 가지 있어요
Encode takes you from strings to tokens, and decode takes you back again.
인코드는 문자열에서 토큰으로 디코드는 다시 과거로 돌아가게 하죠
And we will see that.
두고 봐야죠
And of course, there's just a little bit of nuance and fiddly stuff, but that's basically all there
물론 약간의 뉘앙스와 성가신 부분이 있지만 기본적으로 그게 다예요
is to it.
비트 박스는
A tokenizer contains a vocab, which is all of the different fragments of characters of one character,
토큰이에는 여러 단어가 들어 있어요 한 글자에서부터 네 글자까지 다양한
two, three, four characters shoved together that make up that token.
문자를 조합해서 토큰을 구성하는 거죠
Um, and it can also include as well as these fragments of characters.
또한 이런 캐릭터의 단편들도 포함할 수 있죠
It can include something called a special token.
특별한 토큰이라는 것도 포함할 수 있어요
A few of these special tokens where a special token is again a single token that is going to tell the
몇몇 특별한 토큰은 하나의 토큰으로 모델에게 그것이 나타내는
the model something that it represents, like start of a sentence or beginning of a chat with the assistant
것을 알려줍니다 문장의 시작이나 비서와의 채팅 시작 같은
or something like that.
것을요
And as I mentioned before, if you're thinking, okay, but how do we train a neural network architecture,
아까도 언급했지만 신경망 구조를 어떻게 훈련할지 궁금하실
how do we how do we how do we construct a neural network architecture so that it expects a particular
거예요 신경망 구조를 어떻게 구성해야 특정 토큰이 문장의
token to represent something like start of sentence or something like that?
시작 같은 걸 나타낼지 궁금하실 거예요
And there's no magic answer.
마법 같은 답은 없어요
It just simply comes down to training.
훈련만 잘하면 돼요
If it's seen enough examples in its training data that has that special token being used for that purpose,
훈련 데이터에서 특정 토큰을 사용하는 예제를 충분히 봤다면 그게 그
it learns that that is the objective of that special token.
특별한 토큰의 목표라는 걸 알게 되죠
But there's nothing fundamental in the architecture, generally speaking, that expects one particular
하지만 아키텍처에서 근본적인 것은 없습니다 일반적으로 토큰의 종류를
type of token over another and also a tokenizer.
다른 종류로 바꾸는 것은 없습니다 토큰라이저도 마찬가지죠
In addition to doing this, mapping text to tokens and having a vocab also has something called a chat
이 외에도 텍스트를 토큰에 매핑하고 대화방법도 가지고 있어요 채팅방 템플릿이라고도
template.
하죠
At least for a specific type of model, as we'll see.
적어도 특정 모델은 그렇죠 곧 보시겠지만요
And that knows how to take a set of messages where you've had system message, user message and so on
시스템 메시지나 사용자 메시지 같은 메시지 세트를 토큰
and turn that into just a set of tokens.
세트로 바꿀 수 있죠
And that will all make sense when you see a real example.
실제 예시를 보면 이해가 될 거예요
So every model in hugging face, every open source model has its own tokenizer associated with it.
얼굴을 끌어안는 모든 모델 오픈 소스 모델은 그와 관련된 토큰라이저가 있어요
There's not just one general tokenizer that applies to models because it depends on how the model was
토큰이 한 명만 모델에 적용되는 게 아니에요 모델이 어떻게 훈련되느냐에 따라 다르거든요
The tokenizer, um, I mean, obviously multiple models could share the same tokenizer, but but what
토큰라이저는, 음 여러 모델이 같은 토큰라이저를 공유할 수 있지만, 중요한 것은 어떤 토큰라이저가
matters is which tokenizer was used when the model was trained, because you have to use exactly the
훈련된 모델에서 사용되었는가 입니다. 왜냐하면 실행중인 추론기간에 정확히 동일한
same tokenizer during inference time when you're running it, otherwise you will get back bad results.
토큰라이저를 사용해야 하기 때문입니다. 그렇지 않으면 나쁜 결과를 얻을 수 있기 때문이죠.
Uh, maybe that's an experiment we should try at some point, but I'll you'll see why.
언젠가 한번 해 봐야겠지만 이유는 알게 될 거예요
That would be a very unproductive experiment in just a moment.
당장은 비생산적인 실험이 될 거예요
So for today we're going to look at the tokenizer for llama 3.1 which is the iconic family of models
오늘은 라마 3 토큰라이저를 살펴볼 거예요 라르마의 상징적인 모델 가족이에요
Sorry.
미안해요
From.
네
From Larma.
라르마한테서요
From Mehta.
메타가 보냈어요
That paved the way for open source models.
오픈 소스 모델의 길을 닦았죠
And we're going to look at a model called Phi three from Microsoft.
마이크로소프트의 파이 3 모델을 보죠
And we're going to look at Quinn two again, the powerhouse from Alibaba Cloud, which leads the way
퀸 2도 다시 보죠 알리바바 클라우드의 동력원으로 여러 지표에서
in many of the different metrics.
선두를 달리고 있죠
We're also going to look at something very different, which is a model called Star Coder two, which
다른 것도 살펴볼 거예요 Star Coder 2라는
is a model for, for for generating code.
모델인데 코드 생성을 위한 모델이죠
We're going to look at its tokenizer to see any differences.
토큰라이저를 살펴보고 차이점을 찾아볼게요
Um, and the reason that these two have similar looking graphics is that Lama 3.1 and Phi three are
이 두 차의 그래픽이 비슷한 이유는 라마 3 때문이에요 1과 피3는 굉장히
extremely similar.
비슷해요
Quantu perhaps it's also very similar, but it's it's got more of a focus on, uh, Chinese as well
콴투도 비슷하긴 하지만 영어와 중국어에 더 중점을 두고 있어요
And Star Coder two is of course more about coding.
스타 코더 2는 물론 코딩에 관한 거죠
So with that introduction, we're going to head over to Google Colab and we're going to do some tokenizing.
소개를 마쳤으니 구글 Colab으로 가서 토큰라이징을 해보죠 HDMHD HDMHDDHDHD